SHANTANOO SINHA

+1 (224) 282-5081 | shantanoo.sinha@gmail.com | github.com/shantanoo-sinha | linkedin.com/in/shantanoo-sinha https://shantanoo-sinha.github.io/

SUMMARY

Team player finishing Masters degree in Computer Science & 9 years of software development experience seeking an opportunity as a Software Engineer. Offering a working knowledge of software development, algorithms, data structures, networks, & databases.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer Intern

CME Group, Chicago, USA

May 2020 - Present

- Developed & enhanced the internal web application in C#, .Net MVC, MSSQL, Oracle, ¡Query, SignalR & Excel libraries
- Programmed complex VBA Macro dashboard reports & integrated with the internal application using C#, Oracle, EPPlus
- Created automated testing regression suite in C#, .Net MVC using MSTest reducing manual testing by over 70%

Student Assistant

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, USA

September 2019 – May 2020

- · Provided technical assistance to students, faculty, staff, tenants, guests, and visitors with the campus technologies
- Troubleshooted software applications, computers, mobile devices, printers, phones AV, printer & plotter issues

Software Engineer

IHS Markit, Noida, India

July 2015 – August 2019

- Created microservices based architecture using Java, SpringBoot, Hibernate for the distribution of data to clients and downstream
- Implemented a CLI application in Java, HTMLUnit to web-scrape & download 1000+ monthly trustee reports saving manual efforts
- Remodeled the UI using Angular 6, Typescript, JavaScript & Bootstrap and improved application speed & performance over 50%
- Reduced the application deployment time up to 80% by writing Puppet manifests for 50+ production applications
- Recognized with 'Star Award' & 'Most Valuable Player' award for top performance across the organization

Software Engineer

Tata Consultancy Services, India

December 2011 – July 2015

- Supervised technical direction, mentoring and training for a team of 8 developers
- Developed Timesheet entry & Claim-reimbursement end-to-end web modules using Java, Struts, jQuery, JavaScript & MySQL
- Automated the build and deployment by creating a generic fully automated CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins, GitLab & Docker
- Analyzed and optimized complex slow running SQL queries, improving efficiency by 30%
- Awarded 'Star of the Learner's Group' award in a batch of 40 ILP trainees

Software Developer Intern

Sahara India Limited, Lucknow, India

July 2010 – August 2010

Online Letter Processing System (ASP.Net, C#, MS SQL, Visual Studio)

- Coded a web application to store, forward & review the official documents electronically and automate the management of letters
- Programmed the archival process and created a daily end-of-day batch job to archive the old data and files

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Stock Watch (Java, Android, Android Studio, IEX API, SQLite, Multi-threading, Git) Source Code

September 2020 – October 2020

• Created an Android application using Java and IEX API which allows the user to create a watchlist to view real-time share prices

Peer to Peer File Sharing (Java, RMI, Multi-thread, Eclipse, Git, Vagrant, Fedora)

February 2020 – May 2020

- Designed a Napster style & decentralized Gnutella style P2P file sharing application for linear & all-to-all topologies
- Implemented custom RSA asymmetric cryptography to encrypt network traffic and Push & Pull file consistency mechanisms

Bigdata Analysis of Yelp Dataset (Hadoop, Spark, Hive, Pig, Python, Tableau) Source Code

April 2020 – May 2020

- Analyzed <u>Yelp dataset</u>, created a data pipeline in Hadoop, stored the data in Hive & performed transformations using Spark & Pig
- Presented real-time results using Tableau Desktop visualizations and dashboards

Database Management System (C, Visual Studio, Git, Linux) Source Code

August 2019 – December 2019

• Implemented a small Database Management System in C with a disk-based B+ tree index structure and Buffer Pool implementation

PERSONAL PROJECTS

Flixster (Java, Android, Android Studio, Async HTTP, YouTube Player View, Glide) Source Code

September 2020 - October 2020

Flixster is an app that allows users to browse movies from the <u>The Movie Database API</u> and watch movie trailers

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Language & Database: Java, C#, Android (Java), Python, C, Shell scripting | Oracle, MSSQL, MySQL

Framework: Spring Boot, JPA, Hibernate, Struts, REST API, Hazelcast, ASP.Net MVC

Frontend: Angular 6, JavaScript, jQuery, Typescript, Bootstrap, HTML, CSS, JSON, XML, AJAX, Firebug

Tools & Repository: Eclipse, Visual Studio, Jupyter Notebook, Markit (CADIS) EDM | Puppet, GitLab CI/CD, Jenkins, Maven | Git, SVN

EDUCATION

Master of Science – Computer Science Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago 3.3 August 2019 – May 2021

Bachelor of Technology – Information Technology Gautam Buddh Technical University, India 3.0 August 2007 – July 2011